The people of this indigenous town, between Costa Rica and Panama, let themselves
guide along the path of nature.
At some point in history they were about to disappear.
They were persecuted for their language, for their religious beliefs,
But they knew how to defend themselves and today they are one of the most numerous tribes
from Costa Rica and Panama.
In this video, we will live with the Bribri ethnic group.
We are located in Limón, south of Costa Rica,
and today we have come to live with people belonging to the Bribri ethnic group,
an indigenous group made up of about 15,000 people divided
between Costa Rica and Panama.
Although actually having a very specific number is a complicated mission.
The Bribri speak their own language and have their own religious beliefs.
and they are widely credited with their mentality to be able to coexist with the environment.
It is a culture that respects nature,
who believe that replanting once harvested, in killing species
responsibly.
And this is reflected in many aspects of their traditions.
In this video I plan for us to go on an adventure, to take walks through the woods.
Rainy, let's talk to the locals and learn a little more
about this beautiful culture.
Well come on, normally I would say let's give it a go, but we are in territory
Bribri, so I'll say Mishka.
The Bribri are well known for their very large properties and their houses
built with materials directly from nature.
It is quite common for families to own large areas of land in
those who have orange, papaya, yucca, vegetable crops, etc., etc.,
and that the nearest neighboring family lives
maybe 300, 500 m, up to a kilometer.
Their houses, as we can see, are made of wood, straw,
with extremely resistant soils and they are very proud of this type
of architecture, especially because it is very well adapted to its
weather conditions.
For example, check out this house back here.
This is a house made of cement, metals, glass, etc.
I am told that this is an example of an initiative that the Government had
many years ago, in which to do a good social action,
They came and said: We are going to give you some houses that are good, that are not made of wood, that
these may be less simple, etc.
The intention may have been good, but the result was not,
because being here inside with the very high temperatures,
They tell me that here the average temperature is 30 degrees Celsius all year round,
because it is extremely uncomfortable.
You would need fans all day, even air conditioning.
And since most of the homes here in the forest get electricity
with solar panels, well of course it's not like there's plenty of energy.
So, many of these have simply been abandoned or are used as warehouses.
or they have simply demolished them to rebuild tall houses in their place
with wood, because beyond being, so to speak, simple and old,
They are well adapted to the type of geographical conditions.
It is very interesting to see the history of indigenous peoples,
because we have always survived with nature and that
This makes the indigenous population continue to survive to this day.
And something very important, transmit this from generation to generation
generation, because we need it, not to continue polluting nature more.
Look, down here at the house they have all the technology for solar panels.
Here's my good friend, Fabricio. How are you, bro?
Everything is very good. How good, all your anise.
All your anise, as I tell you.
Let's see, tell me, how does this work?
This is like a bit of a complex system, the solar panels are up above,
they capture energy alone.
What it does is transmit it to what it does is transmit it to what it is
the battery, the battery is responsible for storing it and this is a converter,
What it does is convert it and give energy to all the houses we have.
How many people live on this property we are on?
12 people and there are like eight different houses.
And all the houses have lights.
Hey, do they have internet here or not?
Of course, we have the Internet.
We have a large Internet network, Kolby, in this territory.
So, does everything arrive here safely? Everything arrives here very safely.
There are towers, there are signals, maybe by wiring.
We have all the modern technology too.
I know that in this plant it is called Chomta, it is usually used to build
homes, especially the floors of houses.
They grow a lot, despite being so thin,
See how high you reach and become, my guide tells me here,
that is up to twice as high as this.
Look how interesting, I just met Wala here, how are you Wala?
I'm very well, thank you very much, it's a pleasure to meet you.
No, the pleasure is all ours.
Wala has a very interesting story, he is telling me,
She's from France, right?
Yes, I am from France, from an island in the French Antilles.
The island is little known, it is called Mariala.
And now, she lives here, lives together and learns Bribri in return.
to teach a little French to the local children.
You could already speak Bribri, I mean, have you included a conversation?
I would say no, but a few words..
My name is Wallah.
Mia, mia, means thank you.
And you, who fell in love with the Bribri culture here, what did you like about it?
I like nature.
I like everything that is ecological, not too much garbage, being able to recycle.
And there is no waste here.
When it comes to water, things get a little challenging.
Now, depending on the season of the year, because they tell me that most
of water they use is by rainwater harvesting, that is,
catch the rain directly from the sky and ration it so that it can last long.
Look, of course, there are months when it rains and everyone is happy.
and all in abundance, but the planet, especially in recent years,
is very unpredictable.
You never know when a long drought will hit you and if so,
Yes, they have to climb on the horse, go to the nearest river and bring it
its very good bottles.
One thing we have as Bribri is to respect nature.
Why do we have to do it? It's a Bribri principle.
I have to maintain this same thing for four generations of me.
So, I have to keep in mind that I have to leave
something safe for my grandchildren.
That is why today I have this joy, this happiness, sharing and living
life face to face, as we say.
Here with Lorinda we are cooking in a very authentic way.
What are we going to prepare today, Lorinda?
We are cooking homemade chicken and we are going to cook it in guacho.
In guacho, guacho which is a herb.
Guacho is chicken with rice, together.
My eyes are already watering from this fire.
And look, it's really interesting how we're not using any gas, I mean,
Everything is like that with wood, I mean, do you cook every day, Alhorinda?
All times. It is, but fascinating.
Of the ingredients we're going to use for cooking, have all of them grown here?
Yes, like cilantro, with chili.
Do they eat very spicy food?
Yes, we put in some, but not too much either.
And that chicken we're going to devour was also from here.
From here, from the house.
What a sustainable way to gain weight.
The greenest Luisillo el Gordillo segment we've ever had in
the existence of the channel.
Since they cook everything with firewood, look how the roofs of the houses are
They are turning black, they are smoking.
But I am told that this is, in fact, a positive thing that makes the material
lasts longer, because when it is burned it is less attractive to pests and such,
They can last in this state for perhaps 13 to 15 years,
until they need to be renewed.
I am fascinated that even the dishes are made directly from nature,
Using this type of leaf, which I am told is colloquially called sik, they cut it,
They fold it in a certain way so that it is very resistant.
No man, it's delicious and you just finished eating.
The boots, no more washing them there, for the whole family.
Very resistant, very cool.
Let's try the guacho.
Applause for the chef.
It was a 10.
At the time of this document, it is estimated that there are about 10,000 people
who speak the Bribri language, something like two thirds of the
total estimated population of the ethnic group.
This is because many children who are being born are no longer learning.
through their parents the language.
Likewise, they are very exposed to the language that is
spoken in the rest of the country and the continent in general, which is Spanish.
But many families do take care of this tradition of continuing to teach their children
children, grandchildren and great-grandchildren speak Bribri, because it is a part
fundamental to their cultural identity...
......
Talking about a little indigenous philosophy and also saying that God
bless you and God keep you.
What
I'm glad you came to visit me
and these who are here are my family.
Until just 20 or 30 years ago, the Bribri language had no
way of being written.
It was around the 90s that some foreign linguists
They intervened and said: So that the language can more or less
survive, we have to learn to write it.
And several models were made of how the Bribri language should be written,
which of course, is not an easy dynamic.
They did it with the Roman alphabet, with the alphabet, with the same letters
that we use for Spanish, for example, but with different accents
and different punctuations that mark intonations.
For example, I am learning that in Bri Bri there are many nasal sounds,
how you have to sing like this.
So when that's the case, you have to underline the words.
Of course, an example of this is, for example, in the words house and pot.
House is said u, with an accent more or less like this.
Pot is called u.
I'm probably not saying it right, but you have to say it with your nose.
and likewise, when you write it, you have to underline it.
This word is a good example, see, if we read shulé, just like that, shulé,
It means a little animal from the forest.
But if we pay attention to where the nasal sounds are underlined,
shulé means guava.
And things get a bit ironic when we learn that many
of the elderly, already older, Bri-Bri residents, they do not know how to read Bri-Bri
and they don't know how to write it properly.
Even though they have been speaking the language all their lives,
It is their mother tongue that they mainly use to communicate with their
friends, family, neighbors, do not know how to read it and they get very complicated with it
how difficult the pronunciation is and how it was attempted to translate it into writing.
Still, excellent intention on the part of the linguists and only the future
will dictate whether Bri-Bri will be a language that will remain.
The Bribri word, that is, the letters, were not left in writing.
God leaves us with a Mayan key, naturally, that comes
from birth with us.
Those writers invented it and they tell me that I speak Bribri, but if they send me one
leaf speaking bribri, I can't read it.
Many years ago, we were punished for speaking Bribri.
For example, they would hit him with a ruler, a meter stick, let's say,
who doesn't speak that language.
Really, like that.
Yes, I mean, they only told you Spanish. No speaking allowed.
what do you think?
They left him locked in the classrooms and many of us were born and raised
With that trauma, I could think about it.
And things get really complicated when we get into the topic of
that a child is considered an authentically Bribri indigenous person,
has to have a Bribri mother.
The father doesn't really matter, a local woman might fall in love
from someone from outside and as long as she is from here and has a clan,
then the children will receive an indigenous Bribri clan.
But if, for example, the father is a local who falls in love
from an outsider, her children will no longer be able to be authentic
Bribri indigenous people and that could perhaps cause them a problem in the future.
a question of claiming the land, a question of having the land.
How are you?
It is extremely complicated and fascinating that everything is defined by the mother.
The Bribri indigenous culture formed the different clans, uniting them in pairs.
Women are the ones who inherit the clans.
So on: Look at the clans, the children, my children, it is my clan.
If I have a daughter, that is my clan.
My children's wives, no longer, that's a different clan.
And anyway, here among the Bribri, the clan goes for the mother.
What a delicious day this is, breathing so cleanly,
talking with wonderful people, learning a lot.
Right now we're just chilling and I brought a little bit of Big Bad for
toast, because of course, Big Bad is now available in Costa Rica.
Ask at the liquor store near your house, at the grocery store,
the lady from the corner store.
And they already have a very bad brand of good Luisillo tequila liqueur,
tamarind picocito, so we can take a shot.
By the way, did you see? The cover is a shot.
Let's serve ourselves, let's relax.
Salucita, our friends said, BriBri, Betina, pura vida.
What a treat! Let's continue the adventure.
The way people get around here has to be either in
motorcycle or on horseback.
And what really strikes me is how, since everything is your own initiative,
All the little paths we're seeing and such, it's not like they're really works.
of government, but it is from the same premises and they have their signs, see.
Horses, here, very clear.
So, the horse has to go this way, the motorcycle this way.
Maintains order very well independently.
We are learning how to make chocolate here.
We roast the cocoa, cocoa that, of course, grows here.
It has been ground for quite a while now and we will proceed to demolish it,
to tear it to pieces.
It was a lot.
Excuse me here, excuse me.
Mem, I already left here... There's no more chocolate.
There is no more chocolate.
Excuse me, guys, excuse me.
He is asleep there.
Okay, just let her do it.
He said to me: Drop it, I said: Flap, right?
Now what we have to do is separate the shells from the fruit,
as such, of cocoa.
Once we have separated the shells, now we are going to make a Nutella
homemade, you'll see.
You have to hit it hard. Wow!
Look at that, like while I'm spinning it?
It is filled there with Tasty Nutellita, Nutella Bri-Bri.
Wow! How tasty.
And look, there it goes dripping down below.
It looks so macro delicious.
After so much effort, so much effort, now we have to swallow it.
This is a tasty way to gain weight.
Here good Johnny put some bananas on the firewood, he already took them out, he sliced them,
We put Bribri artisanal Nutella inside and made some
Authentic Choco Bananas. Come on, enjoy.
How delicious and it tastes much tastier knowing that it took a lot of work.
And besides, it is a very healthy dessert, it is all natural, no sugar
added, a delight, a delicacy.
In terms of religion, the Bribri are a polytheistic people.
They believe in many deities, the deity of the sun, the moon, the rain.
They are dictated a lot by nature, but they believe in a great creator
which is called Sibú.
Sibú is the one who gave us everything we have in this world and is the one who guided the Bribri
along the way to respect nature and taught them what fruits are
can eat, what animals can they live with, what plants are
that can cure you.
An ahua welcomed us into his temple.
What ahua is the name given to the local healers who were
dictated by Sibú himself.
If your family does not have a lineage of 'awá' or 'awapa', which is the plural,
You will never be able to be a healer, because this was not dictated by the supreme deity.
Sibú told each Bribri clan: It will be your turn to harvest for
the community, you will have to raise the dead, you will have to heal,
you are going to be an 'awá'.
The 'awapa' use herbs to treat any type of illness.
They have a kind of magic stones, which are called sian,
which they carry in a small bag that only they can access.
In fact, one of the local beliefs says that if someone who is not the ahua
manipulates these little stones called sian, rather than doing them good,
Rather than curing them, they could make them worse.
For a person to become an ahua, he or she must have a teacher, who
It is usually his father or his grandfather.
And in addition to herbs, they also often use animal parts to heal.
Mr. Lisandro, the ahua, who very kindly received us and has
talked about, has, for example, heads of monkeys, rodents and even
the beak of a toucan, which to make, so to speak,
patient scans.
Through life, through nature,
It tells you what is wrong with you and how nature itself
can cure you.
Well, there you have it, a little bit.
of the fascinating culture of the bribri.
I have loved being able to live with such, such nice people, learning so much.
of this culture that I find fascinating.
I am so grateful to the locals for welcoming me into their homes.
In your language I tell you, from the heart, host.
Thank you so much for joining me on another adventure.
See you, as always, you know in a few days with a new video.
I'll try to say goodbye in the local language, nasal sound and all.
Good morning..